Hi Pascale thanks for being with us today so we can get to know a little bit more about your role and what you do within CAE.
So to start could you tell us a little bit about your position?
Pascale: Hi thank you, thank you for having me! I'm the Director of Public Affairs and Global Communications at CAE.
Basically CAE is a global company we train pilots as well as you know other crew members in aviation and
What I do is - I'm responsible for the reputation of the company externally.
So it could be you know through, the media or in general the public or internally with employees.
Big part of what we do in a communications team is engage employees, so that's also part of our role.
You know, how you make people within the company feel you know, proud and and externally to increase the visibility of the company
so that people see CAE as a company that they would like to work for or that, you know,
that they would admire. So you know, basically that's the role of Communications.
Also protect protect the company from, you know any issues, crisis, etc by you know,
preparing the messages or doing the strategies that will you know protect.
So basically it's protection and promotion in a way of the company.
Iris: I come from a Comms background as well so I fully appreciate that you know,
reputation management is such a big part of that job. Now, you've been with CAE for 20 years which is such a success story in and of itself,
but there also come some challenges in being within an organization for that long.
How do you stay passionate and engaged in the work that you do you after after 20 years?
Pascale: One thing that drives me is seeing the company grow and the fact that you're participating in that growth.
Also the fact that I get to speak to people who are around the world every day!
So my colleagues, I could be speaking to colleagues who are in Korea or in the Philippines, the UK, Australia...
So it's incredible. And it's even, you know what? With this this pandemic,
it's even brought us even closer together because we do all these these calls, you know
with people from around the world all the time and it's fabulous.
So this "global-ness" is really exciting. But from a personal perspective,
I love being part of a team where I can coach my colleagues, coach people in the communications team to grow
To empower them. To see the results.
They do things even better than I would in the end so you know, these are all things that bring
you know, feed me in my job.
Iris: I love  the idea of the mentorship aspect of it all because it is so much of what you do,
the further up you get into a company is imparting your wisdom and knowledge and making sure that the
next generation moving up is going to be I guess, better than you were at that stage,
because they have you mentoring them. That's great.
What would you say is the coolest thing you've gotten to do you in your current position?
Pascale: Let me put it in two ways-
We work with really cool technology. So I remember one day when the A380 simulator was ready and I went there
and we were filming something for you know for communications and I got a chance to be in the cockpit
and actually land the A380 simulator! That was really exciting, I remember that.
Like, you know I'm basically landing this huge plane.
So but apart from that- apart from the cool technology,I would say
the the coolest project is a long term project and it's basically helping you know "evolve" the culture of our company.
So there was a time a few years ago where engagement in the company was really low
and in terms of the communications team and the HR team, and you know we all got together
and it's a long process but we started you know trying to see how we can get engagement up in the company.
For instance, around the 70th anniversary of our company, we did like a whole year of celebrations.
A whole year of recognizing people for what they did.
A whole year of giving back to our people, giving back to our our employees.
And we saw like a huge change in engagement, and we saw how we had an impact on our people
and how you know people became more engaged in the company and the work became easier for everybody.
So basically, I was proud of that- proud of the impact that we could have you know with with what I do.
Iris: It is nice to see sort of the evolution and you know when you're working for a big company,
it is sometimes hard to see yourself as a change maker and everything.
But to have that ownership, of the program and to positively influence internally engagement and culture is such a huge thing.
Congratulations on that!
Now if you could ask your role model in the industry anything, what would it be?
Pascale: I don't have a specific role model in the industry.
I'm not sure if we're talking about the industry in terms of aviation or industry in terms of communication,
but I would say, that one thing that I would ask, for instance people that I admire-
who have a lot of charisma, you know Obama or Gandhi or anyone like that is
"How do you make people feel important and and make them feel better?"
So for instance, these are leaders who speak to huge crowds.
They touch the whole world.
But when you listen to them, it's as if they're talking to you specifically and that's what I find you know,
this it's very inspiring and I, you know, I would love to know, what can we do to have an impact like that?
To touch people in that way.
Iris: I think that's a goal for so many people is how to, you know-
how to reach many but also at the same time reach the single person because that's where the change comes from.
So much, it's one person holding onto your words, holding onto your inspiration and moving
It forward internally and pushing it that way so that's great.
Pascale, thank you so much for joining us today it was great to hear more about your role and the
impact you're having on CAE and I fully appreciate your international experience because
that's how you and I got to meet, thank you very much for joining us today and have a have a great day
:)
Pascale: Thank you so much Iris for having me, it was really nice to see you again first of all,
it's true it's been I think you know maybe 10 years?
Thank you for this great initiative of having these interviews.
:)