Hi Allison, thanks for being with us today so we can
get to know a little bit more about your role with Porter Airlines.
Allison: Good morning
Iris: To start, could you talk a little bit about your position?
Allison: Absolutely, I am currently the Director of
System Operation Control, also known as SOC.
My day to day responsibilities kind of really depend
on how the airline is operating in the day.
So if we had a blue skies across the network you know, I'm with
my management team working on technology and
process improvement, communication, those types of things.
But, if there are resource shortages or weather challenges,
it's all hands on deck in that Ops Center.
So it can be a little challenging at times and often your priorities
are rearranged for you at a moments notice.
You know, you need to adapt, but it's certainly very exciting
and no day is ever the same.
Iris: And how did you move into your role?
Allison: I came to Porter Airlines about 7 years ago
as a Duty Officer. So that position is really the point person
in the day to day operation and it gave me a chance to learn
Porter's operation and also kind of exercise my decision making skills
with, you know, a new business. And then after 3 years I was promoted
to the manager of SOCC and I've been in my most recent role for 3 years.
A little bit of luck, a little of bit hard work and I've been fortunate
to move up quite quickly.
Iris: That's great, sometimes it's better to be lucky than good.
So you manage a team, I'm curious, how big is the team and
what qualities do you look for when hiring?
Allison: I have a team of about 55 in various positions. All different
types of qualifications but if I were kind of to put everything
into one bucket- to kind of come into the operations centre.
you certainly need to have some sort of basic aviation background
And the learning curve is quite sharp even once you're in the op centre.
But you do need to have a you know a good comprehension
of technology, you push a lot of buttons in SOCC- pun intended,
and you know, you need to be able to multi-task, make decisions
and you have a really high self standard and pride in the work
that you're delivering.
And you need to care- not only about the people within the business,
but also our passengers.
Iris: What would you say are some of
the challenges that you faced in your career?
Allison: You know, I would get to those junctures in my career,
when opportunities would come up and you really have to decide
what you have to take...
And I would feel extremely isolated and really not know who
to turn to for support in my immediate community and family.
I didn't really have anybody that had been in aviation
or business the way that I am so, I think that's why mentorship
is just so important. It can be so difficult to maneuver through
those crossroads and you know, it would have been nice to
maybe have a little bit of guidance and helping hand.
Iris: What would you say is the coolest thing you got to do in your role?
Allison: Oh, my job is so cool!
I get to do puzzles all day long, so I even have one that
looks like Tetris, if you're old enough to get that reference...
But I also joke with my colleagues you know, we push up our glasses
because you know we're like "oh... What's ATC doing?"
and "What's happening with that runaway closer in Montreal?"
and "What altitude is the tropopause at?" You know
But seriously though, we get to problem solve all day.
You always get to figure out new ways to do things, because no two
situations are the same. And you really get to navigate new territory
all the time and it's so rewarding. You make decisions and things
turn out and it's very, very rewarding.
Iris: If you could ask your role model in the industry one thing,
what would you ask them?
Allison: I think to kind of take this into two veins,
it would be you probably around mentorship a little bit, you know.
Is there anything that I'm missing? What are my blind spots?
You know, what don't I know that I wish I knew?
And then it's kind of on the failure side.
Because you know, we all fall down from time so I would want to know
you know, "Did you ever trip? What caught you off guard and
how did you get back up again?"
Iris: Those are great questions! And if you could share one piece
of advice on building success, what would that be?
Allison: Again I'm sorry, I have two but I promise to make it quick!
I would say the importance of diverse experiences.
There is no one path forward, and just get out there and try everything.
But you know, the aviation industry can be a little bit intimidating
and you know, don't be scared about the things you don't know,
you just simply don't know them yet.
Iris: That is great advice, I'm going to take that advice.
Thank you so much for joining us today, it was really great getting
to understand a bit more about what you do with Porter Airlines!
:)
Allison: Thanks so much.