Hi Beth, thanks for being with us today we can get to know
a little bit more about you. So to start off,
could you talk a little bit about your move into aviation?
What compelled you to explore career opportunities within the industry?
Beth: Hi Iris, hanks for having me!
So in retrospect it looks like this was a deliberate plan,
but it really wasn't. I started my career in engineering and high tech.
I knew that I was never going to be an electron guru,
but I really liked the business side. I went and did my
MBA in the Netherlands and then moved to the U. K.
and joined a management consulting firm there.
I worked in predominately, sort of heavy industries, like I
had contracts in the North of Scotland and England working
on railway maintenance, and in paint factories
in France, Germany and the Netherlands and all of that gave me an appreciation for
the operational side and the efficiency side of business.
At the same time, I had that the opportunity to travel for work,
but also for leisure, around Europe, Africa and Asia.
When I moved back to Canada, I joined Aeroplan which started
as a six week strategy project and grew into-
I've now been a part of that organization now for over 11 years.
And really I had a number of interesting roles, all underpinned by-
you know an application of math and data to business performance.
Also I particularly liked being able you know,
now inside of Aviation, being able to relate to our customers.
You know, working in management consulting I, you know,
I worked in a conveyor belt factory- so I really couldn't
relate to the product. Where as, in aviation, you know travel
and my interest in travel, I can directly relate to what we're trying to do.
We fast forward to a few years ago when Air Canada acquired Aeroplan,
I was asked to lead the integration of Aeroplane into
Air Canada, and I knew at the moment I started to meet
the people inside the airline and get an appreciation for
the leadership and how the airline was run, I saw this as
a great opportunity to be able to apply what I've been learning elsewhere
and apply and then learn a whole new industry.
And so as I said, I didn't start, it looks in retrospect
like there was a deliberate plan but now, you know,
now it all makes sense and you know I'm I'm thrilled to be part of it.
Iris: Who would you say outside of your family has had the biggest impact on your life, and how?
Beth: Well, I'm an avid observer of people.
Some call it curious or nosy, I prefer to think of it
As an "observer". So I take inspiration from everywhere.
So I like to think that there are lots of people who have had
an impact on me. You know, I've been very fortunate to have had an influential,
very influential swim coach growing up in high school.
I've had a number of really good bosses who, you know,
their appreciation of my strengths and the belief in me,
has had impact, direct impact, in the role I was in, but almost more
in retrospect I draw upon the conversations that we had and
the belief they had me in my subsequent roles.
Iris: What are some of the key lessons that you learned in your
previous roles that helped you prepare for your work in aviation?
Beth: Aviation is renowned for its complexity
and for all of the different lingo and and sort of "inter-connectedness"
of the industry, and I think you know, I draw upon
good management consultants, listen to their clients, they're not experts themselves, and the role of
management consulting is often  sort of listening to,
and piece together what everyone's telling you
in order to be able to formulate a plan, apply some structure
and help adhere to that plan, deliver the plan.
I feel like, you know me having that as my background, it's been
really helpful you know I'm often sitting and listening and
trying to piece together all of the different elements in order to
be able to learn and build my business accumen in the airline industry.
Iris: What would you say are three things that are crucial to creating your own success?
Beth: I think for me it's about having a plan it doesn't need to be,
you know, a "micro-plan" but more having a general plan,
and then having the confidence to rely on that plan.
And then I think the third probably is to seize opportunities you know
this isn't about... I can picture in my head you know,
times when I was patient and then sort of saw an opportunity and then
was able to seize my way into either evolving you know,
shaping a different project or taking on a different role,
but it's not being afraid of sort of identifying those opportunities, and then seizing them.
Iris: Ok, so now it's time for our fast answers round-
I'm gonna ask you a few questions and if you could just say
the first thing that comes to your mind- we'll get through this!
Best aviation moment you've had?
Beth: I think probably the best was one of the first and then at
the time I didn't even know it.
Air Canada celebrated her 75th anniversary a while ago and I was
invited to participate in that- not as Air Canada but as part of Aeroplan.
At the time they were unveiling their new Dreamliner, and I think
going into it I had no expectations. Then you know, I remember coming
away from it saying "That was really cool!" like I didn't know
I was interested in airplanes and then going on that Dreamliner and
sort of seeing what it was like... and then also, sort of
seeing all of the culture and tradition and the evolution of the airline.
I love that! I eat that stuff up!
So I think those two things together where the starting point for
you know where I now, thankfully ended up inside aviation.
Iris: What is a difficult challenge you've overcome?
Beth: I've been very fortunate throughout my career to have been supported
all the way through but it has been an industry-
or has been a path that- there aren't as many females.
You know, through engineering and management consulting, and even now.
I think some of the challenges, interestingly, have been you know
kind of challenging my own beliefs. I remember there was a project,
like a super difficult project we had, and there were three females
on the project. We were young females, going and trying to change,
you know a very steadfast industry who were held in their beliefs...
and I remember, you know I remember kind of questioning myself.
Can we even do this?
And my bosses never wavered, didn't even consider, you know,
not bringing in a male to help it because they believed so strongly
in that we could do it, and we did!
So I think I use that as right, now when things are hard I'm like
"Well if I did that, I can do anything!"
you know, or this doesn't seem that hard vs. how that went
Iris: "What do you think is a strength of yours that's help in your career?
Beth: I think being able to learn quickly and the kind of assimilate
and connect dots quickly, I think has helped me along the way.
You know, I'm not an expert in anything and so you know,
being able to understand well enough and connect it to something else
I think has helped me.
I also think, I'm an introvert so I and I'm very aware of
how I get my energy is about you know being able to figure stuff out myself
and being in my head, working usually with sort of data or structure
and figuring stuff out and I think, that too has helped me of
being able to apply that pull myself away figure something out and then
kind of come back to it and being able to apply that in a way that adds value
Have been strengths that have helped me along the way.
Iris: What is something new that you've learned in the past year?
Beth: For me, I think, as I said, the Airline industry is a complex one,
and so it's been nothing but learning over the last year, and I loved it!
It's everything from how the different pieces fit together and the
sort of interplay between the different teams and departments to the airline lingo
to being able to sort of connect what different views of our data
and of our performance and how do those pieces connect together.
So I feel like a year and a half into the airline industry, I've been on this
super steep learning curve and I've loved it!
Iris: What is one piece of advice you would give your younger self?
Beth: Believe and trust your gut. So believe in what you think.
You know, rely on your gut. Be it a good thing or a bad thing, and
so you know if it feels right- go for it, if it doesn't feel right-
just you know, cut it loose right then and there
and I think, you know that's something that I've built over time
with having the confidence to believe in my gut and I think you know,
I sort of wish I knew that before, it wouldn't have meant I
probably would have made different decisions differently but, I probably would go after them quicker had I had that confidence.
Iris: And then the last question, what is one thing you want to achieve in
the next twelve months?
Beth: I would love you know, to be able to contribute to the recovery of
the airline. This has been a crazy last six months and I'd like to be able
to use this crisis as an opportunity for us to come back even better-
more data driven, more customer centric, and stronger.
As a team, as a company, as an industry over the next twelve months.
Iris: That's great!
Thank you so much for taking the time to join us today Beth!
:)
Beth: Well, thank you.