So over the years, as a pilot, I've had some great
opportunities to visit many different countries,
meet many different people, it's been fascinating actually.
And I would say that as you grow up, you understand the value
of being accountable and you don't really know what that means,
Until you actually experience it.
You know- your parents can tell you, your friends can tell you,
you can see it from others, you can read about it-
and I think that something that was really remarkable for me,
was the time that I was deployed in Afghanistan flying the Hercules
and you know, you work autonomously, you've got a crew,
And you fly around intra-Afghanistan and stuff and you do
remarkable things actually.
So, the thing that really strikes me as you know,
A growth period in my life, was this particular deployment.
When we landed and we picked up a load- in general
you get this matrix of what you're going to have.
Every day you're leg 1 - leg 2 - leg 3,
and you're going to offload this load and onload that load-
but really they're all completely wrong!
This one particular day, we landed and the load that we received
Was completely not what I expected.
You know, and it required me to use all those decision-making
tools I had in my bag and you know, make a decision-
"Do I take the load, or don't I"
So I decided to you know go back to the Herc,
the engines were running, you know my headset cords dangling
into the back of the cargo compartment, I'm talking to the loadmaster
and some of the special forces that were meeting us at the plane
and I thought you know, everything seemed legit,
it seems safe, there was no issue with you know,
foremost the safety of my crew and the aircraft so I had about
35 seconds between you know, leaving the back of the ramp and
getting back to the cockpit to decide
"What am I going to do?"
Because I knew exactly, when I plug that headset cord back in,
that my whole crew would be you know, waiting...
"What are we doing? What's going on? What's your decision?"
So you know, I plug my headset in, and I put my seat belt back on, and you know, I decided
"Ok, we're going to take the load. We'll take it, and let's go."
So we took it, and we finished our day. We dropped off the load
at destination and you know, I got back and it was weighing on my mind,
to say "Well really, was that the best idea?"
You know, was that the best decision?
And you know, at the end of the day, like that was a huge lesson for me
because it was the best decision for me as far as taking the load
Was concerned but, you know, I had to take a lot of time after that
to explain to the leadership why that decision was good.
Meanwhile, the whole crew was nicely tucked in their tents,
sleeping away and here I was being accountable for my actions and
I was very much responsible.
It was a lesson to me that there was nobody else responsible
for what's going on in that plane. That ultimately, it's me.
You know, you hear about it, we teach it, you read about it,
but until you go through those lessons in life,
to be accountable for your decisions and your responsibility and
take that seriously- then you're really hoisted on board.
So I think accountability, in general, of who you are-
is really something that has marked me.
In the words I choose, in how I treat people, everything!
It all comes to me. So I think that's something that if I
were to talk to my 2 daughters for example, and I would express to them, you know,
What should I -what should you shoot for in life?
Well first of all, you have to be mindful of who you are.
Who are you and what you want to do, but then you know it's...
you have to take accountability for your actions and who you are
and what you want and take those steps to create the life that you want.
Because if you know, 20 years goes by and you're not happy in the situation-
That you know, you're kind of wondering, "what happened?"
Well, you're accountable for that. So, if I were to sum up
all of that- this opportunity to be a pilot, and make those decisions.
The accountability of those decisions is really mine.
I think that's a great opportunity and I'm really happy to have chosen
a life as a pilot or in aviation in general where are you have the balance
between safety and excitement and satisfaction of working with the team and people
and ultimately though, I'm responsible. The self-growth you get from that is,
you can't compare it to anything else.
So I would say that you know, for everyone here -
that's joined in on this exciting Canadian Women In Aviation conference,
I'm happy to be a part of it and I know there's lots of
other stories out there that..
And great, strong, women that can contribute to this
great connection, this great conversation that we're having.
Yes so be accountable...
that would be my story.
:)