Hi Joelle, thanks for being with us today
so we can learn a bit more about what you do.
Could you tell us a little bit about what a flight surgeon does?
Joelle: A Flight Surgeon is a type of medical officer
and a medical officer is a physician in the military.
Flight Surgeons practices a specific subset of medicine which is aviation medicine.
A lot of people, when they initially hear "Flight Surgeon",
They think we're up in a plane doing surgery which honestly,
I think would be pretty cool but that's not what we do.
We maintain the like really strict medical standards
for air crews so they're able to do their jobs.
We're also responsible for flight safety investigations,
Aero medical evacuations -
if someone gets sick how to get them home,
and we provide an advisory role for operations
in between all that, we're also acting as like
a normal family doctor treating patients and air crew
but those are all the additional skills that we have
that we get training for to be able to work as a Flight Surgeon.
Iris: I was probably one of those people who thought that
you were doing surgery in the air so... ha ha ha
Joelle: Honestly I didn't know it existed either
until middle of medical school and when I found out I was like "I would love to do that!"
Iris: What made you the best candidate for the role?
Joelle: I think that my background really provides a strong knowledge base.
So I have a Bachelor of Science in Astrophysics,
A Master of Science in Quantum Physics,
and I am a private pilot and all of those things
together provide a different perspective into
providing medical care for air crew.
So being a pilot myself I understand what it's like to go see,
whether it's your civilian medical provider or renew your air crew, like you are worried about going.
You don't want them to say that you can't fly and I understand that worry and I think
that gives me an opportunity to interact with air crew differently
and hopefully take down some of the barriers that exist
between the flight surgeon and air crew.
I'm not super vocal about being a pilot but some people know
and I think that can bridge the gap.
Iris: I bet you're able to really alleviate some of the stresses
for the pilots and everything with your perspective so that's great.
What are some of the challenges you've faced in this role?
Joelle: A lot of people join the military to do roles that
they couldn't otherwise do in the civilian world. For me, that's being a flight surgeon and doing
all the interesting things whether that's flying in the jets,
Or deploying, or going on exercises, aeromedical evacuation-
but because of the pandemic a lot of those things have been canceled this year
and so that's been a struggle to accept that this is a different
time and I am getting a different experience for better or worse and accepting
that this is this year's journey.
Iris: "This year's journey" is going to be the sort of the caption for this year
Joelle: Yeah haha
Iris: Different for everyone haha so...
If you could ask your role model anything what would it be?
Joelle: I honestly think that I would ask them to hang out at a bon fire
Or go for a walk and just get them to tell me stories
because you can learn a lot about a person and how
they got to where they are just from hanging out.
I love hearing stories and I love getting to know people one on one that way and that's what I would request.
Iris: A woman after our own hearts! We are a big fan of stories and we
totally appreciate the idea of how much you learn from those stories!
So what you say is one of the coolest things you've gotten to do in your role?
Joelle: Fly in the F-18 Hornet for sure ha ha.
Yeah, the most powerful aircraft I've ever been in and probably will ever be in
and yeah... Whole new perspective.
I very much respect what those pilots do on a day to day basis.
Iris: Yeah I can see why that's trumping your list of coolest things ha ha!
Not that many people in this world who are able to say
"Yeah I flew in an F-18, no big deal"
Joelle: Mmmhmm!
Iris: Very cool!
If you could share one piece of advice on building professional success,
What  would it be?
Joelle: You have to first define what that means to you
not based on what other people think professional success is,
and then from there once you have your goal, try to make a path or plan
on how to get there because a lot of the time, it's just those "every day" actions
that will lead to the end result, not like the final push.
Being able to get up every day and work towards it, is the most important thing to accomplishing those goals.
Iris: Defining things for yourself is so important because you can't look
at other people and think "okay that's the steps that I need to take"
It's so unique to you and it so important to define your own success and
not what success looks like to the outside world.
So I think that's really great advice.
Thank you so much for being here, Joelle!
it was so lovely chatting with you and getting to know what the heck a "Flight Surgeon" does!
That's awesome!
:)
Joelle: Thanks for having me!