Hi Joelle, thanks for joining us today so we can get to know a little bit more about you.
First, could you tell us a little bit more about yourself and
how you became interested in aviation as a professional field?
Joelle: It's always been a dream. I am Metis and I grew up in northern Ontario
and I lived on Black Sturgeon River and there was a lot of
float planes that would take off from there and land and I would watch them and
I would watch them and I always dreamed of being a pilot but I don't think I ever actually told anyone.
I wasn't, I guess, confident enough to believe that I could do that.
I pursued a bunch of other things in the mean time,
I have a few degrees in astrophysics, quantum physics and I went to medical school
and finally I felt like I could pursue aviation and got my recreational pilots license.
From there, I was trying to figure out how I could combine all of my interests
which are quite varied, and I found out that there is a job
called Flight Surgeon in the Canadian Military and there's an
area of medicine called Aerospace Medicine.
From there, I set my goals and I last year I actually accomplished
the goal of becoming a Flight Surgeon in the Canadian Armed Forces and
now I'm working towards pursuing an Aerospace Medicine Residency and also
continuing my flight training to become a commercial pilot.
Iris: Talk about a whole lot of stuff!
I mean so, for me, I didn't know "Flight Surgeon" existed, so
when I was introduced to you, my mind was fully blown because  I was just like
"Oh my gosh that's, so cool!"
Congratulations on being able to explore so many different facets of aviation and everything.
So what are some of the opportunities that you found through aviation?
Joelle: Your world honestly gets open to so many things in so many ways
that you wouldn't have expected.
For me when I was thinking of doing some flight training, I had no idea
where to start and this community of women in aviation just like,
exploded in such a wonderful way!
In Thunder Bay, where I was doing medical school at the time,
there's a group called the Ninety-Nines and that chapter there
is the "Sleeping Giant" chapter and I reached out to them and talked to a few of them
who are actually now really wonderful friends and mentors and
I went to Tim Horton's and had a tea with one pioneer and she told me what I had to do
The community is so welcoming, for example, like I've been flying and
I've had some issues with the plane I was flying,
on New Year's Eve like someone will come out and help you fix your plane
so it is second to none. The community is one of those things,
another thing is, I would just say like, adventure.
I've gotten to do things that I never would have imagined.
A few months ago I got to fly in the F-18 Hornet which is crazy and amazing!
I got to do my my own adventures in a plane that my partner and I own.
Fly to Nothern Canada and explore you know the vast wilderness.
The last thing, I actually met my partner through aviation
which is really special because we share that love.
Iris: The community is really, it's so embracing and it's so warm and you're just,
almost taken aback by how many people are willing to welcome you and support you
when for so long, I imagine you probably felt a little bit alone or something so, at least I did!
Joelle: I've never been a part of a community so willing to give and support.
I've been trying to give back by taking young women flying in you know
their first familiarization flight and I think everyone wants to pay it forward.
Iris: What is the best piece of advice you've received?
Joelle: One person that I look up to in so many ways once told me that I was worth it.
and it sounds like such a... I don't know maybe a lot of people
Already know that but for me, it's taken a lot of growth and confidence
to be able to believe that I deserve to be in these communities.
So whether it's aviation, or medicine, or the military...
It's that kind of support or just that base line, like
"you deserve to be here" is a really important sentiment that sometimes we get lost in.
Then another thing recently someone told me is "Don't let people tell you no"
and there's obviously a way to do that respectfully and tactfully but in order
to accomplish some of these goals and you know, be able to excel, I think
that in the back of your mind will help move you forward.
Iris: Women in particular I think, under-value their worth and their deservedness
and keeping that front of mind I think is really really important
for all women, in all stages of their career.
Joelle: mhmm
Iris: So you you have a lot of passions and so we're calling you a "multi passionate person".
What advice would you have for other other women out there who
have many passions and want to do it all like you are?
Joelle: My advice would be whatever you're doing, whatever stage of life you're in,
Or area you want to pursue, always be true to yourself.
That can be hard at times depending on the culture that you're working in,
or culture that you come from because they don't always match.
But I think the second thing, if you surround yourself with positive people
or supportive people, which I would say- Women in aviation 100% is, you'll be able to excel.
Then also being able to, pick your battles.
There is always going to be something that doesn't work out right, or the way
you would hope, and occasionally you're really gonna have to
put your effort in and try to change that, other times you can accept it.
Knowing when to do that is an important skill to learn.
Iris: And it feels like that knowledge of which battles to pick is something
that only unfortunately comes with age. Sometimes an experience of
"that wasn't my fight, that should not have been the fight that I chose." Ha ha
Joelle: We're gonna live and learn and make mistakes...
Honestly, that's when you're going to grow the most.
It's the hardest part of the journey, but when you look back-
That's what defines you.
Iris: What is the best aviation moment you've had?
Joelle: One of my one of my favourite memories, or I guess moments was flying
In my Piper Cherokee over the Churchill River. This was in the spring time and
The Beluga Whales actually go there to have their babies in the spring,
and I looked down and I saw honestly like a thousand Beluga Whales!
I didn't expect to see that.. My partner with man and he honestly like jumped
out of his seat with joy and I don't know how I could ever top that moment.
Iris: I for sure thought the F-18was going to be there,
but I really think that you trumped it with the beluga whales ha ha.
Joelle: That was cool too ha ha
Iris: What is a difficult challenge you've overcome?
Joelle: Being an Indigenous person passing with the dominant society-
I have blonde hair and blue eyes, sometimes puts me in a situation
of being a wallflower you could say.
And I frequently hear colonial, inappropriate, racist remarks and
I guess one of the challenges has been to find my voice and to be able to
speak up when I feel safe in those situations and trying to calculate
If that's the moment or not, and understanding that it's okay
if I can't speak up or understanding the benefit of doing that
in that moment to support myself, to support where I come from and who I am.
That's something I'm still learning about and I'm trying to be better at
but that's the challenge that I face frequently.
Iris: And I imagine it's probably a challenge you're going to continuously face
And continuously learn new ways to overcome and manage.
What is a strength of yours that has helped you in your career?
Joelle: Curiosity and also willingness to learn.
Iris: What is one piece of advice you would give to your younger self?
Joelle: I would tell young Joelle to embrace who you are,
Embrace where you come from and also where you want to go and
do that regardless of what people say to you or behind your back
because you have to be able to believe in this *gestures to self*,
Not what's out there.
Iris: If you could tell my younger self that too, that would be really beneficial ha ha .
What is something new that you've learned in the past year?
Joelle: Yeah so going back to the F-18, I learned how to do a loop
So that was pretty cool ha ha. But I also learned like
obviously we have the pandemic in the back of, I guess our lives right now,
Or the forefront for me as a doctor, but isolation is really hard on everyone
and that's something I've learned.
Iris: We're all gonna have so many challenges coming out of this pandemic
from mental health perspective and the aloneness that we've had to experience.
Joelle: mmhm.
Iris: What is one thing you'd like to achieve in the next 12 months?
Joelle: I would like to deploy, that's one of my goals in the military
and I'm also trying to get my commercial pilot's license. Those are two of my goals.
You have to have goals you know maybe I won't meet them but, I'll try.
Iris: Stretch goals are a really important thing in life!
Joelle: ha ha yeah
Iris: Joelle, thank you so much for joining us today and letting us get to know
a little bit more about your I think this is,
you're going to be inspiring to a lot of women out there just to take a chance
and try as many things as you can and- you're proof! You can do it!
So thank you!
:)
Joelle: Thank you thanks for having me.