Hi Sheena, thanks so much for taking the time to talk
to us today so that we can get to know a little bit more
about you. To start, can you tell us how you became interested
in aviation and how you came to work in the sector?
Sheena: I actually came into aviation on total- by chance actually
it was not... originally I was in the Oil & Gas industry in Alberta
and I will say I had  somewhat of an early "mid-life crisis"
I wanted to do something different with my life, I wanted
Something to do a bit more meaningful. I'd actually applied
to university and been accepted for teaching in Alberta and it didn't
feel quite right, so I looked at the military option and I thought
"You know what, I'm going to be 30 soon" and I didn't want
to have to like get a huge student loan and debt and I was like
"I'm going to go the way of the military, get an education,
get it paid for, try something completely different,  completely out of my element"
And I put in my application, and a little while later,
I was accepted, And here I am now.
Nisha: How did you end up picking the trade of AVN Tech?
Sheena: I had a couple different options that I had higher up,
but I talked with my uncle who is an AVN Tech actually and
I had a little discussion with him about some of the other traits
that I was looking into and he kind of like swayed me towards the
AVN Tech side of things. I had actually even had my application
to be a clerk too because that's what I was familiar with
so it was like my backup ha ha.
Yeah an option basically, but I got lucky and I got offered
the position of AVN.
Nisha: "Can you tell me about some of the opportunities
that you found through working in aviation?
Sheena: I haven't been in the military that long yet,
it's not even been 8 years. So already I've got to deploy with the
Hercules which is when I worked on. I was in Kuwait for ROTO 0.
We were the first ones out in Kuwait with the Hercules and we got
To set up there, and get things rolling and that was
a huge experience in itself. I also got to- with
a lot of begging and pleading because they were short on my crew,
I got to go with Op Renaissance in Indonesia when they-
for disaster relief in 2018 I believe it was.
One of the huge reasons I wanted to join to get to help
other people and it was... that was what made the struggle
to get where am worth it, just in that one trip I feel.
I've got to fly to a lot of different places, see a lot of places
I don't think I ever would have seen unless I'd joined the military.
Even I was lucky enough to get spend about a month in France doing
some training on some different stuff for the aircraft out there.
It's been a lot of different experiences and traveling the world
and meeting a lot of people, bonding with people that-
You don't really think you'll get to bond with people
as much as you do, until you're going through the training and
the traveling and working in super close confined areas
with them on the aircraft, so it's been very rewarding so far!
Nisha: I love that you created some of these opportunities
for yourself by asking for them!
Sheena: I was 100% on my knees begging my sergeant
to just let me go! Because we had a shortage
of Techs at the time- which is very typical haha
and we, on our crew, there wasn't a lot of people and they were
trying to call a couple other AVNs to go on the trip and I'm like
"You're not finding anybody, please let me go!" Haha
So, yeah.. They finally gave in and let me go on the trip.
Nisha: So on that note, what is the best piece of advice that
you've ever received?
Sheena: When I was a young teenager I don't remember the age exactly,
but my granddad said to me
"Smile, it'll get you really far in life vs walking around with a
Frown on your face"
and for some reason, it always stuck with me and I try to always
be positive and optimistic about things. Sometimes it's difficult
but then it's just like you know, it's much easier to take what you can
And make it a positive outlook instead.
Nisha: What are three things that you think are crucial to creating success ?
Sheena: Hard work. 100% hard work.
I don't think I would have gotten where I am today without hard work
and determination, sometimes if it feels difficult you just
got to keep going through it- just know that you're
working towards an end game.
And also don't be afraid to get into uncomfortable situations
because if you stay in your happy little comfortable zone,
you're never gonna really experience everything that you could so...
Be uncomfortable haha
Nisha: What is your best aviation moment?
Sheena: 100% helping with the disaster relief in Indonesia.
There was one point where I was on the plane and we're flying
some of the people there out of the disaster area and we had
like they all had just a little bag of belongings but they were so happy and so grateful!
Nisha: That sounds like such a rewarding experience!
Even though it would have been so difficult at the time that you
were going through it.
Sheena: There was a lot of little kids there that we helped,
so it was... they were just so happy and thankful haha <3
Nisha: What is a difficult challenge that you've had to overcome?
Sheena: I would say for myself the most difficult challenge is...
my size. I'm not even quite 5'2" a lot of the gear in military is
made for people that are taller than me.
A lot of the equipment that we use is heavy.
A lot of times when I was on the flight line,
working with people.. They would see my size and feel like
they needed to help me do things.
Which kind of motivated me into sometimes work a little bit harder
Or overcompensate which isn't necessarily the greatest thing to do
but I think as people started working with me they saw
that I was capable, and if not then I would just ask for help.
And I would try to find times that my size was beneficial.
Like my hands are kind of small so they fit nice  in tight spots in the engine.
So I would find times when I was useful to climb into
the little tiny areas to get the jobs done
that other people couldn't fit into or stuff. So you've just
got to deal with it, but that is 100% one of the more
normal day to day struggles I have. It's just my size haha
Nisha: A lot of times when we look at like "paving the way"
and what that looks like, we forget that this is exactly
what it looks like. It looks like challenging the everyday stereotypes.
Finding ways to show people that being different is not necessarily
a disadvantage. So thank you for doing that
for the other AMEs  that are coming up behind you that are small!
Sheena: Just do what you have to do in order to enjoy your life really.
Nisha: What would you say is a strength of yours that
has helped you in your career?
Sheena: My hard work. I have a pretty strong work ethic I like to-
and it can be to a detriment too sometimes.
Sometimes I have to like, remember it is a job...
I still have to like remember to breathe sometimes,
let the work stuff like just kind of not be hanging over my head so much
But, it's something that I take a lot of pride in so I will
give a job or task everything I can and then it means a lot to me
and my career is what means a lot to me so  yeah.
I would say, my hard work and determination.
Nisha: What is one piece of advice that you  would give to your younger self?
Sheena: Have more confidence in yourself ha ha.
Don't second guess yourself as much as you did and just,
know that you can do things when you put your mind to it.
Nisha: What is something new that you've learned in the last year?
Sheena: I've learned how to tile! Haha
I did a bathroom reno and it sounds so weird but it's something
I've never done before haha.
And I was doing tiling and I get in "the zone" when I'm working
on little detail things and I just kind of like, tune things out.
So it could be a good thing or bad thing but I loved it
but I hated it at the same time.. It was just like
every little measurement and it's very detail oriented and yeah
I was pretty proud of the fact that I got to work on that.
Nisha: I think that state of focus is called "flow"
and it's supposed to be really good for you, so I'm glad you got
to use it in a project that brought you so much joy!
And my last question for you is-  what is one thing that
you want to achieve in the next 12 months?
Sheena: I would love to travel again but probably not
going to happen with all the restrictions that we have in place
right now... However I'm planning currently for
a back country trip for camping in Algonquin and
I'm kind of looking forward to that, it's something that
I wanted to do for a very long time and I've never had...
I could have taken the opportunity but I guess I was a little bit scared.
So we have a friend that is very experienced at that so we're
kind of piggy backing and getting a first experience on that one,
so I'm really looking forward to it, hopefully all the restrictions are lifted
so we're able to get out there and  actually give it a go.
Nisha: Well Algonquin is a beautiful place to do something like that,
I hope you get to do it and I hope you have a blast!
Sheena: I'm hopeful, thanks!
Nisha: Thanks for joining us today Sheena,
and for talking to us about how you got into aviation.
It's really great to get to know you a little bit better.
:)
Sheena: Thanks again for me chatting with me,
it's been fun!
:)