Hi Sheena, thanks so much for taking the time
to be with us today so that we can get to know a little bit more
about what you do you. To start, can you tell us a little bit
about your position?
Sheena: Normally when you start as an AVN Tech,
you're working directly with the aircraft.
You're training, you're working directly with aircraft,
you're working on problems with like fuel snags or
hydraulics for you can be fixing/changing a tire,
you could be parking an airplane. There's a lot of different
things that you're doing, hands on, outside, different weather-
rain, snow.
It's- any day is different when you're out on the first line. That's what I did for a
good chunk of my career so far.
Following that, I went to an office position where I was looking
At paperwork making sure all the airworthiness paperwork
was correct and that was a very big learning experience also.
And then from there, I actually applied for a QULLIQ
which is what I'm currently working with, it's a small team
That was started up in 2020 and basically our job-
it's a very big scope but currently we're working on improving
communications within RCAF, and we're basically being formed
As an enabler for innovation within RCAF. So we're
kind of helping the doers out there, "do the innovation" and
We're kind of in the background trying to connect all the people
that need to be connected in the right spots.
Nisha: What made you apply for a position on the QULLIQ team?
Sheena: So it was very different. Right from the get go,
it was just completely different way to get on the team.
It's not typical to apply for a position in the military,
in this one, it was taking an application-
there was a very broad scope of what they were looking for,
previous experience that I had with some project management
and office skills and stuff.
I kind of have that experience and then I had "on aircraft"
experience. I did a little bit of flying with aircraft so
I kind of saw some of the aircrew side of things. So,
I kind of ticked off a lot of the boxes that they
were looking for but, I had no idea what they were actually
gonna be doing. There's not really any full, clear guidelines
Of what your job would be, so I put in my application and
Thought that I have nothing to lose from putting in an
application, so I might as well!
and it just sounded exciting because I didn't really
know what I would be doing.
People ask "Why did you even apply for it?" And I'm like -
Because I didn't was going to be doing, like I could be making coffee for
people or I could be doing something..  I didn't know!
and it kind of sounded interesting in that way.
Nisha: What unique strengths do you bring to the team then?
Sheena: I like doing little tasks, I like getting organized,
I like helping people get organized so I think there's that.
I try to stay pretty positive I'm hard worker I think all those
kind of are good skills and just all the general different
experiences that I've had in my life pre-military and with
the military I think it helps give a different viewpoint
on things that we're tackling and working on.
Nisha: What is the coolest thing that you have gotten to do professionally?
Sheena: There's been a lot of really cool things!
Again the helping with humanitarian aid in Indonesia was
probably one of my highlights because that's one of the reasons
I joined because I wanted to be part of something that was
Making a difference in other people's lives.
It was 2018 and I went with a small crew, we were helping
With disaster relief in Indonesia when things were
pretty rough for people down there so we were helping
fly people out of disaster areas and flying supplies into
The areas that needed it. We were working with a lot of
different countries and it was neat to see all the different
people working together and just to help each other out.
It was an experience I won't forget any time soon.
The people in Indonesia are amazing!
They're all so happy and like positive and...
I loved it there haha!
The kind of have a piece of my heart for sure.
Nisha: Yeah I always think it's really so touching when you
go to a place that's been impacted by a disaster and you still
see this vibrant kind of like, welcoming culture.
I think that's probably one of my favourite components
Of traveling with the Air Force to these
different parts of the world.
Sheena: Yeah, 100%!
It's something that you don't soon forget.
Nisha: If you could ask your role model anything,  what would it be?
Sheena: I don't actually have a role model.
There's never been any one person in particular
that I looked up to. I sometimes learn from what I feel is
defeating for myself and think I don't want to do that
for other people so I kind of try to like,
Learn more from the bad stuff that happens.
As weird as that is and then try to think
"Hey I want to do better and I want to like, be the best person I can be"
and not necessarily look to somebody else. Everybody has
their own experiences in life and whatever got somebody else
to the spot that they are isn't going to be the same kind of
experiences that are going to get me there, so I feel like
it's just best to work on your own self development.
Nisha: First of all I think making your own way is a really
great approach, but I don't think it's really weird to
learn from the bad things that happen, it's just a
different way of thinking about things. Different people get
inspired by different things, and I think I'm the same as you.
I get inspired by wanting to continuously improve and so I'm constantly looking
for different ways that I can learn from
my environment, on how I can improve myself right.
So I wouldn't necessarily call that weird, and my last
question for you today is- what is one piece of advice
you would give someone on creating professional success?
Sheena: Go for what motivates you.
Don't go for what other people think you should be doing.
Go for what motivates you and makes you happy and fulfilled
and I think that will bring a determination to yourself that
will motivate you and help create your own success.
Live for yourself basically, don't live for other people.
Nisha: I love that piece of advice.
I think it took me awhile to get there, but living that way
has been really rewarding.
Sheena: Myself too! It's something that, it takes awhile
to get to know that part of yourself and accept it, but I think
it's the best way to go for myself, so far anyway.
Nisha: Takes a little bit of time to figure out where
you want to go in life and it's worth it to spend that
time trying to figure that out. Thank you so much Sheena,
for joining us today and for sharing with us what your
work looks like. We appreciate your time!
:)
Sheena: Thank you very much for having me again!