So when I was a teenager, I lived in Alberta
and I had seen a lot of people up in the Cold Lake area
in uniform when I was driving my sister and myself up
to get our braces worked on.
I'd seen them in uniform and I kinda thought
"That looks pretty cool"
However, I didn't really have the confidence in myself as
I got older to like 18, 19- I didn't think I could join the military
I guess I didn't think I had what it took to be able to
successfully get through basic training. I was never considered
an athletic child, at all! I was more of a
"sit and read a book and hangout by myself"
I went into a regular route. I guess in my own thoughts,
I had to do that typical-
Grow up, get a job that was easy to
accommodate getting married and having kids.
I never really thought outside those kind of options.
As a people-pleaser I always kind of felt like I had to do
what was expected of me and I think that's just mostly an
internal pressure. It's not even something that anybody actually
said to me  like "K, this is the way your life has to go"
but that was just an internal thing that I had growing up.
and it's just again, part of my personality and just trying to like
keep everybody else around me happy. I went the route of working.
I got a job in the Oil & Gas industry. When I hit about 28 or 29,
I'd actually been depressed for a couple of years with my life.
Early mid-crisis I guess you could say....
So... I got help and...
I'm glad I struggled through the time that I did because
it enabled me actually later on in life to reach out and help people
That suffered with mental illness and stuff.
I needed to change, I needed something changing drastically in my life
So I could be happy and feel a bit more fulfilled.
I had thought originally that it would be to teach.
I thought that would be a good way to give back.
But it didn't feel right for me. One of the reasons was because
I was 28 / 29 at the time and I didn't really want to take on
a full student loan. I looked into other options and I had.
I had decided- You know what? I want to change my life and
I want to do something that gives back and I wanted to
take a big challenge and so getting outside of an office
and getting out of the line of thinking, I went and you know,
and I said "You know, I'm going to put in my application for
the military, I'm gonna see what happens and if I can do it!"
I didn't have a lot of support, or not a ton...
My family didn't think I'd ever make it through basic training
but I think in a way that kind of fuelled me a little bit more
To actually prove to myself that I CAN do something
if I put my mind to it.
I managed to get through it. I remember calling my mom before
we went to the field for basic training and I said
"I'm packing my bags, we're getting out there, I'm excited!"
and she said to me, "You know what?
I didn't think you'd make it. I just did not think you would make it
through to this point,  I thought you would be home by now."
And it just kind of was like "No and I got this!"
Not that it was all easy! There were some struggling days haha
but I got through it and I think basically, I just want people to know
have confidence in yourself, it's super hard to accept that and you
have to build the confidence in yourself with all
the experiences that you go through in life, but I think,
once you realize that you can make it through things-
it helps build your self esteem, and just know that even if
you do try something and you fail... Take it as like a learning
experience and figure out what went wrong and grow from that.
Don't let it hold you back from trying again or trying something different.
I don't think military is necessarily good for everybody and honestly,
A couple times I second guessed it. Because when I was a younger girl
I had a friend that was in the Air Cadets and she was
always trying to convince me, she was like
"Come on, join! It's great experience!"
and I'm like "I'm not wearing a uniform, I don't want to polish my boots
or anything!" haha and now.... Here I am
So whatever you think is right at one point in your life
doesn't necessarily mean it's going to be right for your whole life.
Have confidence to change what you need to change to be happy!
And go from there haha
:)