Hi Sophia. Thanks so much for joining us today.
Can you tell us a little bit about how you got into the field of Aviation?
Sophia: Hi Nisha it's lovely to be here, thanks for having me!
I'm from a small town in southern Alberta called Crowsnest Pass and we had a gentleman that moved into my little neighbourhood and
he just was like the kind of person  that I would say "oozed cool" and he actually said "Sophia, you should join Air Cadets!"
and I was like "Nooooo..." You know, I get picked on and I was chubby and just like not in a good spot in my headspace.
Later on we found out he's a fighter pilot with the Canadian Forces. So no wonder he "oozed cool" right? He was one of those people.
One of those "Amazing, look what you've done!" kind of people. But he kept encouraging me,
So finally, I just did it so he would stop bugging you need me
I joined, and I didn't like it at first at  all, I had to go put my hair
up in a bun, ironically. I had to polish boots, I had to learn how to iron
I was like "Oh this is no fun, this is too hard!". My parents actually taught me such a huge lesson then that I'll never forget:
"No no no, you signed up for this. Give it an honest try, give it a year. If you still don't like it after a year, fine you can quit"
I grumbled and whatever else and I started actually liking it. I'm loud, so I started getting good at drills and the marching side of it and the commands of it.
And I started making friends and just feeling like I found my community and my place.
Close to the end of that year, this pilot, his call sign was "Midas"
He brought an F-18 down to Lethbridge - I fell in love with that thing!
Like it was just this big cool airplane and I was terrified of him and everything, still being very insecure at that age.
but you know, walked around and get  to touch it and talk about it and all the stuff at the end of the day,
He went to leave and he took off and let us all stand on the apron and I remember like hands on the ears because it was so loud.
and I just felt my whole body go "Oh my god, this is cool!"
It was like I fell in love and someone hit me over the head and said "Airplanes, you gotta do that!"
Nisha: So what are some of the opportunities you've found through Aviation?
Sophia: The people,  that's my favourite part!
Including yourself and everyone at CWIA. People are generally really excited and happy
There's opportunity to go wherever you want to go with it.
I've got to go all over the place as a pilot.
I've got to go to different conferences as a female pilot and really explore that..
Speaking engagements and just learning different things such as you know,
being on boards and what not as well so, it's endless really!
Nisha: You need to say it again for people in the back because that's another thing that I really love about being part of this industry as well!
What is the best piece of advice that you received?
I'm in the master class with Elevate Aviation right now - different speakers from Kathy Fox with the TSB,
and Nicole Girard with Transport Canada, so many amazing people that give you different advice
it's really hard to go through it all and find out what matters to you at a certain point in your life.
The best advice I ever was given and that is sort of my motto to this day is to aim high and never give up.
I just I try to live by that in general. There's no such thing as dreaming too big, it just might take you longer
Nisha: What are three things you would say are crucial to creating success?
Sophia: Part of it is as believing in yourself and knowing that it's okay when you don't.
I've had lots of conversations with other women in aviation and that's
always a question of "Well I don't have everything on this box ticked off so I can't apply for that job"
or "Well, I'm okay, but I'm not great".
You know, it's all our own self criticisms that will sometimes hold us back.
"OK I can do this, oooh god I'm scared... But I'm still gonna try! ". That push forward-
So I guess, I don't know if you would call that tenacity, but that was a big part of it.
As well as just being able to be honest with yourself about what your failures are
I've definitely failed A LOT and that's okay.
You learn from each of those and you try to get better.
In Aviation, that's  pushed constantly, safety is number one across the board
every time anybody in this whole industry has failed, we've analyzed the heck out of it
and tried to go "Ok, so how do we make it better?"
How do we grow?
How do I make it safer for everyone else?" I love that now, but
it took a while to get used to because it's like
"Oh god I did something wrong, don't look at me!"
But look at me, let's learn, let's grow, let's figure it out!
The other one is- Don't ever bring a bridge. It's a very small industry.
I remember when I was in Aviation College, there was somebody that,
we just didn't click right, I thought "I really don't like this person."
And then I was like "This is mean, I'm being mean, stop it!" and he was kind of mean
and I kept hearing "Don't burn a bridge Sophia, don't burn a bridge"
like later we became friends and I'm so grateful for it,  it's echoed  throughout my whole career
you know being kind to people trying to find ways to
even if you're not going to be best friends. That's okay, but don't burn a bridge.
Nisha: The gravity that your insecurity has; especially as a young woman I find that you have to work
so hard to overcome that. The last thing you said about Burning Bridges, man I can tell
you I feel that right now some days. That's phenomenal advice
to kind of take that long-term perspective on things.
What is your best Aviation moment?
Sophia: You know what actually the top one would have been November of 2019
I was honoured with the outstanding alumni award at Mount Royal
and I was really excited to be there and nervous  about it
and my husband couldn't come but my mom and my dad and a bunch of friends came which was amazing.
My dad who I recently lost in the last 6 months, he was very hillbilly
and I got to go up there and talk about aviation
and my dad in a full on voice goes "HOW TO GO 'PHIA!!" ha ha ha and tha crowd!
was like I was just so glad that he was there and was so proud of
me for just being me.
So I think there you go, you're already said you're already getting
me all tearing up just for an important moment. So yeah.
That's probably one of the biggest and best
Nisha: You're getting me tearing up and I never cry!
What is a difficult challenge that you've overcome?
Just being a young pilot and getting used
to it. I constantly was like "Am I good enough for this, am I smart enough to do this?"
I didn't have a ton of mentorship. I had Push and Midas, who was definitely amazing,
but I didn't have a lot of of encouragement  especially as a flight instructor.
So going that path was, you know lots of people were like "you'll do that and then you move on"
and I was like "I don't really want to go to the airlines, I kind of like this and teaching
is sort of my thing". So I had a lot of trouble
overcoming that that was okay and that I could make my own path
and do what I wanted to do for my lifestyle my family my desires, my goals
that took a long time and then when I could, it was like this
huge light bulb went off and I could actually make progress with
other things like Elevate, like the Aviation Board and so on and so forth.
Because it was  like "Oh, hey wait, it's ok to be just you and what you want to do"
Nisha: I think you're a phenomenal role model
like, you're huge role model to me as well.
What is one strength of yours that has helped you in your career?
Sophia: Being stubborn, I think has actually been a strength which is funny
because we're often told "Oh don't be too stubborn". My husband is stubborn as well
and we always say like "This is bad, sometimes our stubbornness beats us!"
But, I won't give up, I won't quit. Part of that is that stubbornness.
Even though all that negative self-doubt and all that has been there my whole
life and will continue. I appreciate so much that you think of me as a role model,
but I'm still just me and that's often the case with the people we look up to the most.
Also remembering that they're still human.
That would be the biggest thing that's helped me just continue and
kept pushing through as I was just too stubborn to quit sometime.
Nisha: Persisting after what you really want to go after which is a great quality at the end of the day.
What is one piece of advice that you would give your younger self?
Sophia: Partly just to be more compassionate to yourself. Recently I've been
learning about self-compassion cuz I'm not very good at it.
From like I mentioned before, I was not in a great place when I was 12
I just kind of all of a sudden got chubby between grades like 4 and 5 sort of thing.
I hung on to that for quite a while and I struggled  and I still, I gotta get out of it
you know like I'm trying really hard to be more compassionate to myself
and you know, it sounds silly but like learning
how to self talk in a positive manner to yourself is actually really hard
So I think I would try to encourage my younger self to try to start doing that sooner instead
instead of you know, mid-thirties and I'm slowly starting to try haha.
Nisha: Never ever too late to start but it's great advice to give someone who's young so thank you for sharing, that's great.
What is something you've learned in the past 12 months?
Sophia: It's actually been a pretty good journey! How to Zoom of course ha ha ha ha
and you know, google meetups and hang outs and all these other ones.
Technology  has definitely been part of that. I've been working a lot on trying to figure out a little bit more
about marketing social media and that sort of thing. I've been doing a lot of that
For the Edmonton Flying Club as well as just trying like I said a little bit of self-growth
and the Elevate Masterclass and try to find different ways of leadership learning more about boundaries.
I am the kind of person I get bored easy so I have to keep learning or I'm like "welll I'm bored"
Nisha: What is one thing that you hope to achieve in the next 12 months?
Sophia: I was in a couple of kind of nasty car accidents so
I've got kind of a messed up neck and back
so on a small level  I've been doing a bunch of like P90X challenges
So my big goal there is to try and finish those.
and like, keep going and getting stronger and being proud of myself for that.
On a work level it's just to become a better leader. I'm always striving to learn more in that sense so that I can be
a little bit better for my own team.
Nisha: Well thank you so much, Sophia for joining us today!
It was lovely to have you on and to get to know you a little bit better.
:)
Sophia: Thank you for having me, Nisha!