Hi Sophia, thanks so much for being here with us today so that we can get to know a little bit more about what you do. To start, can you tell us about your position and what it entails?
Sophia: So my main job is I am the Chief Flight Instructor with the Edmonton Flying Club.
So that means I'm a pilot and I teach people how to fly but I also manage a bunch of other instructors who do the same thing at various different levels.
I manage the team, maintain operational control, I adhere by the Transport Canada box and basically
I work with a great team of other instructors who will teach everything from that first private pilot
license from commercial, multi engine, instrument  and one of my favourites is instructing new
instructors. Then with that I am also the pilot examiner. It's for Transport Canada but I do a lot of
the exams at EFC as well.
and it's just you know making sure I'm holding to the standards that are set to try and make the best pilots we can.
Nisha: You're also an active volunteer so could you tell us a bit about what some of the volunteer positions you hold are?
Sophia: Sure, one of my favourites of course is I'm the Director of Community Engagement and
Mentorship with Elevate Aviation. I also am a director or board member with the Alberta Aviation
Museum as well as with the Alberta Aviation Council.
Nisha: Wow so you're part of 2 boards, and boards are kind of these mysterious organizations that
a lot of people in aviation don't know about so could you demystify it for us a little bit? What do you do as a board member?
Sophia: Depending on the organization once a month or once every couple of months where most people
that care about the organization get together and discuss some of the big things.
Especially financial and strategic planning for the future things like that.
So after sitting on a couple meetings at the Flying Club, I actually kind of fell upon the Alberta Aviation one by accident.
I'm a huge fan of the museum, and they felt like kind of slowly starting after the City Centre Airport was shut down;
people didn't know about it, or they thought it closed, and I was at a few different events actually
with Elevate and the Flying Club- you know running a booth at Women in Aviation Day or something like that.
I met the President of the Board and she was amazing and we started chatting a bit she said
"You know the funny thing is, I'm the youngest person on the board I'm 65, and I'm the only woman!"
I just asked like "How do I... Can I help?"
And she says "Well we're actually looking for Directors"
And I was like "Could I try?"
And she said "I will nominate you today!"
And I was just like "Cool! Ok shoot... What did I sign up for.."
So to be honest I kind of fell upon it and fell into it by accident just because I was like you know what,
I'm young or younger than 65 haha and a female and I'd be happy to help.
I love the museum and I'd like to see where it can go in the future and maybe my insights will help a little
or at least I could learn more about who I can look for to maybe recommend somebody to replace me if I'm not the right fit.
So it was completely by accident that I first got into it I guess but honestly it's about meeting and getting together and
trying to think about what the goals of the organization are and how to move it forward
so whether it's financial plans- like during Covid we've had quite a few meetings about what grants
can we apply for and helping the staff find those grants
and helping them find good writers for those grants and you know what can you apply for to keep the staff going
and and that sort of thing so it's honestly it's about having honest conversations for the most part
and everybody has their own background, has their own connections that attribute and can make a board really great and really strong.
Nisha: Can you talk to us a little bit about what the process was like?
Sophia: It depends on the board to be honest.
So with the Alberta Aviation Museum I had to fill out an application form and submit that and then
they put my name towards the board and the President actually talked a little bit about who I was
And a few of the board members knew me so they said "oh yep, Sophia is this and this..."
and then they had to vote on it and go you know "yes, no, maybe so"
Then every year you still get re-elected if you put yourself forward and if the sustaining members of
the organization like what you're doing and feel like you're good to be there
Or it might be the board that thinks that you're good to be there; they'll continue to you know vote you in per se.
Some will do it more formally like at the Alberta Aviation Museum it's really formal.
Others I've seen where everybody just goes "yep, you're good to go, I think you're fine"
or it's "Are there any objections?" and nobody says anything.. "Ok, you're a board member again" ha ha ha
It really depends. With the Alberta Aviation Council, again I was kind of approached and asked to be a part of it.
and and I didn't even know what the Alberta Aviation Council was at that time so it was a really good
thing for me to you know jump in and learn about
and again same sort of thing, my name was put forward and I had to fill out a form about who I was
and kind of what my little bio was and from that I was elected onto the Board.
So it's not a complicated process for the most part.
Some boards like for example; the Edmonton International Airport Board- for something like that,
it's a little more complicated.  There's a bigger application process and you may not get selected the first time but it's also if you
put your name forward once, then you kind of stay in a pool often and later on people might be like
"oh wait, wait, wait, wait - this personal applied a couple years ago and I see they've been doing
really great things, and they have this-  and we need this now, so let's maybe pull them in."
So it does you know it does depend on the board and what they're looking for but some of them are
crazy easy and others are more complicated.
Nisha: It sounds a lot like you just need to take a chance and put yourself out there.
Sophia: 100%
Nisha: Why do you think it's important for women- especially young women, to be part of Boards?
Sophia: I think it's about perspective. You know...
"You don't know what you don't know" is something that I've been thinking about a lot lately because it's come up.
There's so many things I have no idea about, there's so much history in different places
like especially the museum, the Alberta Aviation Council. and I want to learn more too,
So it's another way for me to learn but it's also so that I can carry that forward, right?
Having you know, a more senior Board is amazing but you want to be able to carry that knowledge and not lose it.
You know so if in three years there's a full turnover on the board because a bunch of them have retired-
where's all that knowledge? It's gone!
So if we don't start putting younger people on boards to learn from that and grow and you know
and encourage that like connection.. You're gonna lose all that experience.
The other aspect of it it's just different perspectives different ideas.
Even just you know, you and I - living in different cities, there's certain things that you're going
to think about that I'm not and vice versa
and it's the same thing as being different ages, different gender, race, backgrounds whatever it might be
perspective and that diversity, is huge for growth.
Nisha: How has your volunteer experience helped support your goals?
Sophia: My biggest thing is I want to change the world.
I think lots of us, you know, put it as simple as that.
That's the big dream, I want to change the world and I remember before I found Elevate especially
in conversations with my partner of being like "I just, I'm not doing enough. I feel wrong, I don't
feel whole because I'm not volunteering enough I'm just, not doing anything."
And it really caused me personal heartache because it was like I was missing a chunk of me or something
and in some ways I kind of think that me finding Elevate or Elevate finding me,
that it could help me fill that hole and give me a way to try to work towards the actual goal of you know,
changing the world. It probably is in a very small way and that's ok and maybe I'll hopefully try to  make it bigger and better all the time.
But it's it's just helped me to find that community to work towards those goals and
to learn what some new goals are and how to actually achieve that idea of  "How do I help the world? How do I make it a better place?"
Nisha: A lot of people that I know, especially through CWIA, feel very very similarly and my story
with CWIA is very similar to what you're talking about with Elevate.
"I have so much energy and potential where can I channel it?"
and I just stumbled into this opportunity and took it up.
Sophia: Give it a try! Like what's the worst thing that happens?
You get told no? Then try something else ha ha
Nisha: Yep! Last question, what advice do you have for women who want to get more involved with their communities?
Aside from the "put yourself out there"
Sophia: Don't be afraid when you get told "no". To try again.
It's really easy for that to happen as well. Sometimes it's just about doing some research trying to find what's out there.
Like I said I personally didn't even know about some of these things
and so it was quite literally asking some questions and being curious and letting my curiosity be ok.
I think we're sometimes afraid to ask questions which I'm also personally trying to work on.
Being like "Well I actually want to learn about this"
So I mean you know; just ask the questions and see what it takes you.
Nisha: At times I used to just internalize the "no" as rejection then I said
"Not right now, we don't need that right now"
Nisha: You know, let it pass by right?
Sophia: Yeah, things happen for a reason, and I don't know what it is but it's there ha ha.
Nisha: Yeah, thank you so much Sophia for joining us today. It was lovely getting to know what you do
And thank you so much for sharing your insight into what it's like being a board member on the
Alberta Aviation Museum and with the Alberta Aviation Council.
Sophia: Thanks so much for having me! :)